Okay בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's דף daf is בבא קמא Bava
Kamma קט"ו, kuf tet vav, 115. We pick up on קי"ד עמוד
ב' kuf yud dalet amud bet on the משנה mishna about fifteen
lines from the bottom. I'm recording this in the home of my
sister and brother-in-law, the שבעה shiva home for their son, Maoz Morel,
זכר צדיק לברכה, zecher tzaddik livracha, who died from his wounds defending
עם ישראל Am Yisrael in Gaza last week, and our learning should
be לעילוי נשמתו. le'ilui nishmato. Okay,
we start with we begin with the
משנה. mishna. המכיר כלים וספרים ביד אחר, Hamakir kelim usefarim beyad acher,
if somebody recognizes his vessels, meaning any objects from his home, or
his books, and books at that time of course were scrolls and
very expensive, and he sees somebody else is walking around with his
iPhone and with his תורה Torah scroll or whatever it would be,
ויצא לו שם גניבה בעיר, veyatza lo shem geneiva ba'ir, and it
was known or there was a report in the town that he
had been burgled, ישבע
לו לוקח כמה נתן ויטול, yishava lo loke'ach kama natan veyitol, so
because we presume and the גמרא Gemara is going to discuss this
that that report is accurate, that he had been burgled, then therefore
the person whose hands they're in, nobody is claiming that he's the
burglar,
but this person says I just bought it from a guy who
said it was his. I had a right to assume I bought
it from Reuven, Reuven said it was his. You don't need a
document to prove before you buy something from somebody. But now it
seems that Reuven was a burglar. So because we presume that the
report is accurate, that it was he had been burgled, he has
a right to take back his object. And the assumption here is
that it's before יאוש, ye'ush, so it's his object. It's before יאוש,
ye'ush, so the person from whom it was stolen has a right
to take it back. Now, technically speaking, the one who purchased it
doesn't have a right to demand his money. He has a stolen
item in his possession. Why does the Reuven have to pay him
for it? It's Reuven's stolen item. But what we're going to see
is because of a תקנת השוק, Takanat Hashuk, because of a special
law that was passed, a policy that was passed in order to
make it possible for people to buy things in the marketplace, what
they said was if it ever turns out that the thing you
bought was stolen, then you have a right to get reimbursed from
the original owner. So because if obviously if you didn't do that,
then everybody would have to be very extremely hesitant to buy things.
Somebody's going to come and say it was theirs and they're going
to take it away from me and then I'm going to have
to what, run after the
גנב? ganav? So the person who sold it to me? So because
of the way this would create a real constraint on commerce, they
said you can feel protected when you buy things that even if
it turns out that they had been stolen, you will be able
to get your money back from the original owner. So that is
a תקנת השוק. Takanat Hashuk. Now we'll see in the גמרא, Gemara,
of course, if you had very good reason to suspect they were
stolen, that תקנה Takana wouldn't apply to you, but otherwise we need
to have a תקנה Takana like this if you are genuinely innocent.
Now, how do we know how much you're entitled to be reimbursed?
Who knows where Reuven is? Reuven's absconded. So you have to swear
how much you paid for it and then Reuven will oops, excuse
me, Reuven is the owner in this scenario. Anyway, the person who
stole it has absconded, but you can swear and the original owner
will pay you back. ישבע לו לוקח כמה נתן, yishava lo loke'ach
kama natan, so
the person who purchased it swears how much he paid, ויטול, veyitol,
and he can be reimbursed from the owner. So and then the
owner, so at least the owner gets his object back. All right,
he really wants his iPhone. So okay, he has to pay for
it, but at least he gets it back. And if he now
wants his thousand dollars that he had to pay, maybe five hundred
because the guy sold it to him used, then he still has
to go ahead and find the גנב ganav and now he can
get reimbursed for the five hundred dollars from the גנב. ganav. ואם
לאו, ve'im lav,
but if there was not a report that a burglary had happened,
לאו כל הימנו, lav kol heimenu, then Reuven the owner of the
iPhone is not believed to say oh, it was stolen from me
and you must have bought it from somebody. Why? שאני אומר מכרן
לאחר ולקח זה ממנו, she'ani omer machran leachar velakan zeh mimenu,
because I would say that Reuven went ahead and Reuven sold his
iPhone to Levi and Levi sold it to, you know, Yehuda, and
now Reuven has had great regret and he wants his iPhone back.
So before you can go ahead and start claiming that your objects
are stolen and have a right to get it back if you
pay for it, there has to be something substantiating the fact that
it genuinely was stolen. Okay, so there's a couple of things going
on here. On the one hand, the תקנת השוק Takanat Hashuk is
what makes it protects people from buying things and they don't have
to assuming that they genuinely are innocent and didn't have a reason
to suspect they were stolen, protects those people and they don't have
to be concerned that somebody's going to come along and say it's
stolen goods and take it from me and I'm going to be
out, which would really put a constraint on commerce. On the other
hand, it should be pointed out that we're actually
also sort of being lenient towards ראובן, Reuven, the owner. We're making
him pay, but we're also believing his claim that they were stolen.
And at least as far as the משנה Mishnah is concerned, okay,
there was like a rumor or report. You know, if he claimed
it out of thin air you wouldn't believe him because, you know,
you'll think he just sold it and regrets, but with a
substantiating report and rumor that would be enough. And maybe those two
and normally that's a little strange because wouldn't you need proof that
it was stolen before he can go ahead and take it away
from somebody else? But maybe those two things go together. Since the
guy is going to get reimbursed, לוי Levi who bought it from
ראובן Reuven is going to get reimbursed, therefore maybe we lower the
threshold of what is required for us to presume that it was
stolen. That is a way to understand the משנה Mishnah why it's
enough that there was a report that it was stolen. But the
גמרא Gemara now is going to demand a lot more before ראובן
Reuven can retrieve his objects. So let's take a look. גמרא: Gemara:
וכי יצא לו שם גנבה בעיר מאי הוי? V'chi yatza lo shem
geneivah ba'ir mai havei?
And so what if there's a report that this guy had been
burgled? ליחוש שמא זבנינהו והאי ניהו דקמפיק שמא. Leichosh shema zavninhu vehai
nihu d'kamafik shema. Maybe he sold
it, like the משנה Mishnah said at the end, you know ראובן
Reuven sold it, had regret, is trying to get it back. And
says the גמרא, Gemara, not only is a report not enough because
it's not direct evidence and substantiated, you know, maybe he actually is
generating this whole rumor. All right? So we really should suspect, why
is a rumor any type of evidence of anything? The same way
he could be lying, he could just as easily be generating the
rumor. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב כגון שבאו בני אדם בתוך ביתו
ועמד והפקין בלילה. Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav kegon sheba'u bnei adam
betoch beito v'amad v'hifkin balaila.
Oh there's objective substantiating evidence. Now this is obviously not in the
משנה Mishnah at all. But here's what he says: people actually slept
over in his house and then he got up in the middle
of night and was screaming and says I've been robbed, I've been
robbed. That's the source for the modern Hebrew word הפגנה hafganah which
is a protest. Okay? והפקין בלילה V'hifkin balaila
and he started screaming in the night and said נגנבו כלי, nignevu
cheilai, I've been,
you know, they've been stolen from me. Okay, so therefore it really
does seem that there's substantiating evidence. So the גמרא Gemara says כל
שכן אי לא מצא. Kol sheken ee lo matza. So the
גמרא Gemara says no, you know, this is even more reason to
think that he's just spread this rumor,
that all of this could just be a way of, you know,
he could be manufacturing what, what actual evidence do you have that
people slept in his house at night? That's no real evidence of
anything. And the fact that he yelled and screamed? So, he could
be manufacturing all of that. So רב כהנא מסייע בשמיה דרב. Rav
Kahana mesayei bishmeia d'Rav. So רב כהנא Rav Kahana ended this statement
in the name of רב Rav that רב יהודה Rav Yehuda said
in the name of רב, Rav, he added another aspect that even
more substantiated it: כגון שהיתה מחתרת חתורה בתוך ביתו. kegon shehayta machteret
chatura betoch beito.
No, no, actually there was a tunnel, obviously in the context here
sitting in Israel and with as I said, you know, my death
of my nephew killed in Gaza, the idea of tunnels here is
obviously very evocative.
Anyway, כגון שהיתה מחתרת חתורה בתוך ביתו, kegon shehayta machteret chatura betoch
beito,
there was a tunnel that was dug under his house. So obviously
to think that he dug this tunnel, you know, and these people
that slept in his house at night were sneaking out through the
tunnel. You could also imagine let's say you know, they were seen
climbing over the back fence with and so on. Okay so there's
evidence that they were running away and that they had done something
nefarious. ובני אדם שלנו בתוך ביתו יצאו u'vnei adam shelanu betoch beito
yatza'u
and the people were seen leaving the house וצרורות של כלים על
כתפיהם ve'tzrorot shel keilim al kitfeihem
and like you know big bundles of stuff with like objects were
carried on their back. Okay, so like very much all the evidence
wasn't something that he created, you actually saw the people and it
all looked very much like they had just robbed his house. והכל
אומרים נגנבו כליו של פלוני ve'hakol omrim nignevu keilav shel ploni
and everybody is saying oh this guy's stuff has been stolen and
it's not just some people were saying it's like obvious to everyone.
So there's much more substantiating evidence.
So the גמרא Gemara says ודילמא כלים הוו ספרים לא הוו. Vedilma
keilim havu sefarim lo havu.
So okay, but how so fine they say that his objects from
his home were stolen but how do you know it means also
books? And maybe it's you know because the משנה Mishnah mentioned both
and maybe so it's saying that the actual you know report wasn't
that it contained both of them and maybe also because books probably
were extremely expensive, so maybe we shouldn't assume that. I mean we
should assume that they were burgled but maybe in order to be
get that back you need more evidence. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara says
that wasn't directly part of the report. אמר רב חייא בר אבא
אמר רבי יוחנן כגון דקאמרי נמי ספרים. Amar Rav Chiya bar Abba
amar Rabbi Yochanan kegon dek'amri nami sefarim. Ah
that was part of the report, people also saying oh we saw
that they had stolen books. Okay.
So now the גמרא Gemara continues: וליחוש דלמא זוטרי וקא טעין רברבי.
V'leichosh dilma zutrei v'ka ta'in ravreivei.
Maybe you know they had stolen small books or objects and he's
claiming big ones? You know, maybe he had a what do you
call it an. Android
and he's saying he had an iPhone. So how do you know
exactly that he's telling the truth? Because remember, we're only asking the
לוקח lokai'ach to swear how much he paid for it. But how
do you know that, you know, this guy, even if this, even
if Reuven was burglared, how do you know that Levi has those
burglared items? Maybe, you
know, Reuven was burglared and now he wants to get, you know,
and he sees something Levi has and he'll use the fact that
he was burglared to get it. How do you match up the
burglary with what Levi has? So
אמר רבי יוסי בר חנינא דקאמרי ספרי פלוני ופלוני Amar Rabi Yosei
bar Chanina d'ka'amri sifrei ploni u'ploni because people actually saw it, I
don't know how at all people know this, but people actually saw,
oh yeah, his, you know, iPhone 5 was stolen. They say exactly
what it is. Okay, or his, you know, this particular book. ודילמא
הוי עתיקא וקאמר חדתא v'dilma havei atika v'ka'amar chadta maybe, you know,
they were it was an old version of it and, you know,
and people say I don't know it's an iPhone 10 I don't
know what we're up to. You know, maybe they said his iPhone
was stolen and and it was an iPhone 5 and now he's
saying it was an iPhone 10. Again, how do you exactly match
it up? אמר
רב כגון דאמרי הללו כלים של פלוני הללו ספרים של פלוני. Amar
רב Rav kegon d'amri halalu kelim shel ploni halalu sefarim shel ploni.
Okay, that they directly testify and they say that stuff that Reuven
is holding onto
that Levi is holding onto, we know it used to belong to
Reuven. So basically, you know, this is so much more than the
משנה Mishnah demands, and
but the משנה Mishnah is saying, you know, trying to protect the
purchaser and even if he'll get his money, you know, it's a
burden for him to have to give his thing and to get
back the money and for him to give the thing that he
purchased, you know, even if he's going to be reimbursed. And it's
not willing to accept the claim of the original owner unless it's
very much substantiated. So there has to be some real objective evidence
that
he did not manufacture, you know, some objective evidence that he was
robbed or burglared, and there's also some objective evidence that these were
originally his and therefore you can like connect the dots and assume
that this was actually the object that was stolen. So much more
than is required in the משנה. Mishnah. Now, if you take a
look תוספות, Tosafot, because he's a little bothered because that all, you
know, that sort of seems like they're exactly, you know, that sort
of seems like
it's direct evidence, like it's no, you know,
at least in the משנה Mishnah it seems like there was something
that wasn't totally proven. So if you look at תוספות, Tosafot, he
says: דקאמר הללו כלים של פלוני כלומר כשיצא קול המון אלו כלים
וספרים של פלוני שבני אדם הללו נושאים ואין מכירים שהם חדשים. d'ka'amar
halalu kelim shel ploni klomar k'sheyatza kol hamon elu kelim u'sefarim shel
ploni sheb'nei adam halalu nos'im v'ein makirim she'hem chadashim.
So he says it's not that they say, oh, what Levi is
holding onto is, we know it used to belong to Reuven. No,
it's that when they actually said we saw in the גנב'ס ganav's
bags, you know, we saw an iPhone 10, a silver iPhone 10.
Okay, and now Levi has a silver iPhone 10. So there's still
some jump that we are making, okay, but a very, very tiny
one as opposed to what's implied in the משנה. Mishnah. Okay, but
anyway we're dealing with a תקנת השוק takanat hashuk that when there
is a good reason to assume that this was a stolen object
that now that Reuven is claiming it, and Levi did not, as
we'll see later, I'm just introducing this now, but Levi, you know,
did not have a reason to suspect that it was stolen, but
we now are looking at it and do believe that it originally
belonged to Reuven and it was stolen from Reuven, then Reuven has
the right to get it back because it's his object before יאוש,
yei'ush, but because of תקנת השוק, takanat hashuk, he has to reimburse
Levi. Okay, גמרא Gemara has one more question about this. אמר... Amar...
so where we up... okay. ומי אמר רב הכי? u'mi amar Rav
hachi? Did רב Rav really say this whole because רב Rav described
the scenario that they dug a tunnel
to leave the house. But והאמר רב v'ha'amar Rav didn't רב Rav
say in סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, בא במחתרת ונטל כלים ויצא פטור? ba b'machteret
v'natal kelim v'yatza patur? מאי טעמא בדמי קנינהו? mai ta'ama b'damei kaninhu?
So רב Rav says that case, you know, the classic case in
the תורה Torah of somebody digging a tunnel, the הלכה halacha is,
is that, is that
you're the בעל הבית ba'al habayit is allowed to kill him because
it's assumed that he's coming to, that he'd be prepared to murder
the בעל הבית ba'al habayit if the owner was going to stand
up and try to defend, you know, his vessels.
And so but if he went ahead and he did steal it
and, you know, the owner did not defend, stand up and defend
him and did not lead to his being killed, and he went
ahead and he took vessels and he left the house, because he
was subjecting himself to being killed, רב Rav uses the principle of
קים ליה בדרבה מיניה, kam lei b'diraba minei, even though this is
not a court punishment of a capital crime, you know, it's a
right of self-defense, but nevertheless רב Rav says since he was subjecting
himself to being killed, then we say קים ליה בדרבה מיניה kam
lei b'diraba minei and he actually now owns the objects that he
took. So that... בדמי קנינהו. b'damei kaninhu. So it's a very strange
idea, but it's not our topic right now. Anyway,
so why here does the guy have to give it back? Does
Levi have to give back, right? If שמעון Shimon here's the גנב
ganav and שמעון Shimon owned it because he was בא במחתרת ba
bamachteres so then לוי Levi shouldn't have to give it back. So
גמרא Gemara says הני מילי דקנינהו Hani milei dekanyinhu הני מילי דקנינהו
בבא במחתרת. Hani milei dekanyinhu bevaba bamachteres. That's when he came in
through a tunnel דמעיקרא מסר נפשיה לקטלא demeyikra masar nafshia likatla originally
he was subjecting himself to be to be you know to be
killed. Somebody who tunnels in is assumed ready to kill the בעל
הבית baal habayis if and the בעל הבית baal habayis therefore has
a right to defend himself and therefore he's exposing himself to being
killed. אבל הני Aval hani but these people remember they only slept
in the house and they tunneled out. כיון דלא מסר נפשיה לקטלא
keivan d'lo masar nafshia likatla they never sort of tunneled in and
were exposed themselves to you know to being killed. So לא lo
that would not apply. Okay. So that's point number one really really
raising the bar in terms of the evidence needed to indicate that
it was stolen. אמר רבא Amar Rava said Rava לא שנו אלא
בבעל הבית העשוי למכור כליו lo shanu ela bebaal habayis ha'asuy limkor
kelav אבל בבעל הבית שאינו עשוי למכור כליו Aval bebaal habayis she'eino
asuy limkor kelav לא צריך לההדורי עליה כולי האי. lo tzarich lehadori
alei kulei hai. So he said you know all of these new
demands we added to the משנה Mishna is only if ראובן Reuven
is known to sell things you know he's got an a store
on eBay and he sells used items or whatever out of the
back of his house not eBay okay fine anyway he's known to
sell things that's when you need all this evidence to show that
it really was to make us really believe that it was burgled.
But if this is a guy that normally doesn't sell his household
items then you don't need all of this stuff. Now what does
it mean you don't need all of this stuff? So רש"י Rashi
says you don't need the last point to say oh yes we
know exactly which item was stolen. But the גרא Gra says if
you look at the רמב"ם Rambam it seems like you don't need
any of this stuff and we can go back to the simple
sense of the משנה. Mishna. Okay. So now that's a little bit
restores the balance. We added these crazy demands that weren't in the
משנה Mishna and now we're saying you know what all those demands
might be only in somebody who normally sells his objects then we
really don't believe it. But if somebody normally does not sell household
objects then a much lower threshold to assume that they were burgled.
Okay. ודילמא איצטריכו ליה זוזי וזבין. Vedilma itztarichu lei zuzei vezavin. Now
the גמרא Gemara says even though he normally doesn't sell but sometimes
people you know need money and they do wind up selling things.
אמר רב אשי Amar Rav Ashi הרי יצא לו שם גניבה בעיר.
harei yatza lo shem gneiva b'ir. So רב אשי Rav Ashi retorted
okay that's why we don't believe him without any sort of you
know evidence or without any any indicators. We need there to be
a rumor that there was a גניבה gneiva that he was burgled
but or a report but that's suffice we don't need all the
other criteria. It's true you know it is possible he sold it
but unlikely so as soon as there's a report that counterbalances it
that's enough for him to retrieve it provided that he reimburses. איתמר
Itmar now new topic I mean related topic but new topic three
lines from the top. גנב ומכר ואחר כך הוכר הגנב. Ganav umachar
v'achar kach hucar haganav. Let's say it was like the case in
the משנה Mishna except the difference is that not that שמעון Shimon
stole from ראובן Reuven sold to לוי Levi and then שמעון Shimon
now actually has been caught. All right in the משנה Mishna the
idea is who the heck knows where שמעון Shimon is who
even knows necessarily the identity of
שמעון Shimon okay and it's only between ראובן Reuven and לוי Levi
and that's why לוי Levi can get his money back and ראובן
Reuven gets his object back and if ראובן Reuven ever finds שמעון
Shimon he can get reimbursed. But let's say we actually have ראובן
Reuven and שמעון Shimon and לוי Levi all in front of us.
All right who did does ראובן Reuven still have a right to
get his object back from from שמעון Shimon from שמעון Shimon who
was not the גנב. ganav. So let's take a look. רב משמיה
דרבי חייא אמר Rav mishmeih deRabbi Chiyya amar רב Rav in the
name of רבי חייא Rabbi Chiyya says הדין עם הראשון. hadin im
harishon. ראובן Reuven has to go to the first person meaning he
has to go to שמעון Shimon the first one who who had
his object. שמעון Shimon was the גנב ganav so he you know
and therefore if he can go directly to the גנב ganav even
though his object is still in the hand of שמעון Shimon he
has to deal with the גנב ganav and get reimbursed from the
גנב. ganav. Okay which to some degree makes sense the גנב ganav
is the one that did him a wrong and you know the
fact that he happens to know where the object is the גנב
ganav is the one that he is suing and he's getting reimbursed
from. Okay. רבי יוחנן משמיה דרבי ינאי אמר Rabbi Yochanan mishmeih deRabbi
Yannai amar הדין עם השני. hadin im hasheni. No he does it
with the second guy with שמעון Shimon לוי Levi and presumably because
לוי Levi has his object you know so he gets his object
back from back from לוי Levi and then you know maybe he
reimburses לוי Levi and then he goes after the גנב ganav after
but he has a right to go to לוי Levi and to
get his object back from לוי. Levi. All right and seems like
these are mutually exclusive positions. Let's take a look now how the
גמרא Gemara unpacks it. אמר רב יוסף Amar Rav Yosef לא פליגי
lo pligi they really don't debate. כאן לפני יאוש הדין עם השני
kan lifnei ye'ush hadin im hasheni כאן לאחר יאוש הדין עם הראשון.
kan l'achar ye'ush hadin im harishon. It depends whether there was יאוש
ye'ush you know before it got into the hand of לוי. Levi.
If there was no יאוש ye'ush then he goes else too, then
it's his object and he goes and he retrieves his object from,
you know, from לוי, Levi, and he has a right to get
his object back, and then maybe he pays him for it and
then he gets reimbursed from the גנב. ganav. But it starts by
getting his object back, because it's his object and it's before יאוש.
yeush. But if it was after יאוש yeush and then got into
the hand of לוי, Levi, so לוי Levi owns it now and
therefore his דין din is only, you know, he deals only with
the גנב. ganav. All right, that all seems very straightforward. But now
the גמרא Gemara introduces another factor that's relevant here. תרוייהו אית להו
דרב חסדא. Travaihu is lehu deRav Chisda. They both hold of רב
חסדא. Rav Chisda. If you remember, רב חסדא Rav Chisda at the
beginning of this פרק perek said that if somebody stole and, you
know, let's use the same people, שמעון Shimon stole and לוי Levi
came, you know, באחר ואכלו, ba’achar ve’achalo, and לוי Levi came and
ate it, so רצה מזה גובה ורצה מזה גובה. ratza mizeh goveh
veratza mizeh goveh. ראובן Reuven can collect either from שמעון Shimon or
לוי. Levi. What does that mean? Meaning, and why is it relevant?
It's relevant because the question is, once the object is stolen, what
degree of liability, you know, it's out of ראובן's Reuven's control, what
degree of liability does לוי Levi have, you know, if he damages
it? Maybe it's true, it's still ראובן's Reuven's object, but ראובן's Reuven's
object is very much out of ראובן's Reuven's control. Who knows if
it's ever going back to ראובן? Reuven? So maybe לוי Levi has
no liability towards ראובן. Reuven. Comes רב חסדא Rav Chisda and teaches,
no, if it's before יאוש, yeush, לוי Levi still has liability and
since he ate it, therefore ראובן Reuven can go ahead and sue
לוי Levi as well. In our case, what that means is, the
גמרא Gemara says, that is needed in our case, that principle of
רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, that לוי Levi still has liability. It's still
to some degree recognizing it as ראובן's Reuven's object in order for
ראובן Reuven to go and retrieve it from לוי. Levi. If we
didn't hold of רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, the גמרא Gemara makes it
sound then even before יאוש yeush there'd be no way you could
retrieve it from לוי, Levi, which is funny, it still is his
object. It's one thing if he damaged it, if לוי Levi damaged
it, maybe, you know, you can't sue לוי. Levi. But right now
your object is in לוי's Levi's hands. But what the גמרא Gemara
is saying is look, there's a גנב ganav here, go to the
גנב ganav especially if the גנב ganav is around, you cannot bring
לוי Levi into this, and even though he does have your object,
right? Once it is, you know, if you didn't hold of רב
חסדא, Rav Chisda, you would say that that, you know, your rights
to it are much more weakened. But since רב חסדא Rav Chisda
says that at least before יאוש yeush you do have a right
to sue לוי, Levi, that's why in this case if it's before
יאוש yeush you can retrieve your object from לוי. Levi. Okay, so
what this is saying is is that if both שמעון Shimon and
לוי Levi are present, the גנב ganav and the purchaser, that as
long, if it's before יאוש, yeush, you can, you get it back
from, you get your object back, you can start with לוי Levi
because we hold like רב חסדא Rav Chisda that the second party
is still on the hook before יאוש. yeush. But if it's after
יאוש, yeush, then all right, לוי Levi already owns it and you
have to go to שמעון. Shimon. All right. אמר ליה אביי, Amar
lei Abaye, we just did that. One minute. תרוייהו סבירא להו. Travaihu
sevira lehu. אמר ליה אביי ולא פליגי? Amar lei Abaye velo pligi?
Are you telling me that they don't debate in the after, you
know, they're not really having some debate here? מתנות כהונה כלפני יאוש
דמי ופליגי. Matnos kehunah kelifnei yeush dami upligi. I'll show you a
case of מתנות כהונה matnos kehunah which is similar to the idea
of no יאוש yeush and there's a debate who you go ahead
and have to deal with. So let's explain the case and then
I'll go back and unpack that phrase. דתנן, Detnan, we taught in
a משנה. Mishna. אמר לו מכור לי מעיה של פרה. Amar lo
mechor li me'eha shel parah. Okay, so לוי Levi says to שמעון
Shimon sell me the intestines of this cow. והיו בהן מתנות, vehayu
bahen matanos, and the קיבה keivah was among the organs, and you
know, it wasn't obviously among them. נותנן לכהן, nosnan lakohen, so then
somebody here goes ahead and sells the intestines, the inner organs of
a slaughtered cow. So we will say that here we'll use the
same parties, שמעון Shimon sells it to לוי. Levi. In this case,
ראובן Reuven is a כהן. kohen. So ראובן Reuven is the party
it's being stolen from, because because the קיבה keivah which was in
those intestines as we'll find out, you know, was sold from שמעון
Shimon to לוי Levi and it should have been given to ראובן
Reuven who was the כהן. kohen. So effectively שמעון Shimon is stealing
ראובן's Reuven's מתנות כהונה matnos kehunah that are in these organs and
selling it to לוי. Levi. That's the parallel the גמרא Gemara makes.
Okay, אמר לו מכור לי מעיה של פרה. Amar lo mechor li
me'eha shel parah. Okay, so לוי Levi says to שמעון, Shimon, sell
me the intestines of this cow. והיו בהן מתנות, vehayu bahen matanos,
and the קיבה keivah was among the organs, and you know, it
wasn't obviously among them. נותנן לכהן, nosnan lakohen, so then... לוי Levi
has to give it to the כהן, Kohen, ואינו מנכה לו מן
הדמים, v'eino minak leh min ha-damim, and he doesn't get any reimbursement
from שמעון. Shimon. Why? Because, because we can presume that, you know,
he did not want to steal this מתנת כהונה, matnas kehuna, and
therefore he was always, you know, he never really paid for the
קיבה, keivah, and therefore he has no right to get any money
back. All right, he was always taking it with an understanding that
if the קיבה keivah was there it would go to שמעון. Shimon.
It would go to ראובן. Reuven. However, לקח הימנו במשקל, lakach heimenu
b'mishkal, if it was weighed and he's paying for the weight, then
clearly he is paying unwittingly for the קיבה. keivah. Okay, so he
has given money for something, you know, לוי Levi has given money
to שמעון Shimon for something that שמעון Shimon does not own. נותנו
לכהן ומנכה לו מן הדמים. nosno l'Kohen u-menaki minei damim. Okay, so
then he is, so לוי Levi who has the stomach, has to
go ahead and now give it to ראובן, Reuven, give it to
the original owner, quote unquote, although it could have been any כהן
Kohen which the גמרא Gemara is not getting into. And now he
can go ahead and get reimbursed from from ראובן. Reuven. Okay, so
right, from, excuse me, from שמעון. Shimon. So לוי Levi has to
now give the stomach back to ראובן, Reuven, ראובן Reuven is the
כהן, Kohen, and he purchased it, and he paid money for it
because it was weighed, and he paid money for it, so he
purchased it unwittingly from from שמעון. Shimon. So לוי Levi gives it,
so לוי Levi goes ahead and gets his money back from שמעון.
Shimon. ואמר רב, v'amar Rav, and says רב, Rav, לא שנו אלא
ששקל לעצמו, lo shanu ela she-shakal l'atzmo, that's if that only applies
if לוי Levi did the weighing. אבל שקלו לו הטבח, aval shaklo
lo ha-tabach, but if the butcher did the weighing, הדין עם הטבח.
ha-din im ha-tabach. And in that case, in that case ראובן Reuven
does not take his מתנת כהונה matnas kehuna from לוי, Levi, he
goes and he takes his מתנת כהונה matnas kehuna and he gets
paid for his מתנת כהונה matnas kehuna from שמעון. Shimon. Let's assume
the stomach is worth ten dollars. So in that case where שמעון
Shimon did the weighing, שמעון Shimon is the גנב, gannav, so he
goes even though לוי Levi is holding on to the stomach, שמעון
Shimon has to pay ראובן Reuven the ten dollars and he does
not get his stomach back from לוי. Levi. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says אהא, aha, here you see a case where you have
all the parties, ראובן, Reuven, שמעון, Shimon, and לוי. Levi. If לוי
Levi did the weighing, so לוי Levi is an unwitting גנב, gannav,
fine, he gives it back to ראובן Reuven and he gets his
money back from שמעון. Shimon. But if שמעון Shimon did the weighing,
שמעון Shimon is a knowing גנב, gannav, all right, then comes along
רב Rav and רב Rav says, okay, the גנב gannav is here,
ראובן Reuven deals with שמעון Shimon and he does not go to
לוי Levi and he does not get his stomach from לוי. Levi.
So you see that even though it is before יאוש, ye'ush, because
there's so רש״י Rashi says מתנת כהונה matnas kehuna is like it's
before יאוש ye'ush because since it's sort of God demands it somehow
that creates it gives it more weight and it's not before יאוש,
ye'ush, but what might more mean there's no particular כהן Kohen to
whom it deserve who has a right to it. So since, you
know, you could give it to any כהן, Kohen, so there's no
particular כהן Kohen to do יאוש ye'ush for it. But for whatever
reason the גמרא Gemara assumes that this is like before יאוש. ye'ush.
So you see, it's before יאוש, ye'ush, and even so רב Rav
says, you don't go and get the object back, you don't get
the stomach from לוי, Levi, you deal with the גנב. gannav. Okay,
so that shows you that they really it's not that they all
agree before יאוש ye'ush you get your object back. So let's see
how the גמרא Gemara responds to this. So the גמרא Gemara says
אימא אף עם הטבח. eima af im ha-tabach. Okay, when רב Rav
here says that ראובן Reuven can go to the butcher and get,
you know, and get it back, the butcher who who sold it
to, you know, שמעון Shimon the butcher who sold it to לוי,
Levi, he means if he wants to he can go to the
butcher. Obviously he can go to לוי Levi because the stomach is
still in לוי's Levi hands. But if he wants to, he can
also go to the butcher. Why? Why would I have thought otherwise?
מהו דתימא, mahu d'teima, I might have thought אין מתנות כהונה נגזלות,
ein matnos kehuna nigzalos, that you never since there's not a concept
of stealing, probably again because you could give it to anyone, so
we don't say that when שמעון Shimon weighed it out and gave
it to לוי, Levi, even though he charged for it and he
pocketed it, you know, maybe he sort of stole from לוי Levi
by overcharging him, but there's no act of stealing on this stuff,
this stuff has to be given to a כהן, Kohen, it doesn't
yet belong to a כהן. Kohen. So I might have thought that
the butcher is not considered to have done גזילה gezeilah to it
and therefore you, you know, you wouldn't be able to get it
from the butcher, you could only get the original object back. קא
משמע לן kama shma lan that you can get it from the
butcher. Okay, so here we had a case where it sounded like
you only that even when the object still was before יאוש ye'ush
you had to deal with the גנב, gannav, and we're saying, no,
it meant that you can even deal with the גנב gannav but
not that you had to deal with the גנב. gannav. So now
the גמרא Gemara says ולאביי דאמר פליגי, ule'Abaye d'amar pligi, okay, but
אביי Abaye clearly had a different read. So now we're still dealing
with the claim of this debate of רב חייא Rav Chiyah בר
bar רב Rav and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan where we're saying that
everybody agrees. Before יאוש yei'ush you get your object back, you deal
with לוי, Levi, after יאוש yei'ush you can't get your object back,
you deal with the גנב, gannav, you deal with שמעון. Shimon. But
אביי Abaye was saying no, no, no, I think they actually debated.
I think that there's an opinion that says that even before יאוש,
yei'ush, like this case with the מתנת כהונה matnat kehunah and the
butcher, even before יאוש yei'ush you can only go to the גנב
gannav and you cannot go to the purchaser. So the גמרא's Gemara
going to say, well, if that's true, what's that based on? ולאביי
דאמר פליגי במאי פליגי? ule'Abaye d'amar pligi bemai pligi? What do they
debate? בדרב חסדא, bed'Rav Chisda, they debate רב חסדא's Rav Chisda teaching.
Okay, they debate this principle of if somebody steals it and somebody
else comes and eats it, whether you can have a claim against
the second guy. Once it's already stolen, maybe your only claim is
against the גנב. gannav. Once it's out of your control, even though
it's before יאוש, yei'ush, your ownership is weak enough that you really
cannot make a claim against the second guy who ate it. And
now we're actually saying in parallel, you can't even make a claim
against the second guy who has it in his possession, which is
definitely a bigger חידוש chidush because it's still your object. But okay,
that might be the debate, whether actually even before יאוש yei'ush you
have a right to get your object back, at least provided that
you can go ahead and sue the גנב gannav without dealing with
the whole discussion about the תקנת השוק. takkanat hashuk. Okay, so right
now we have a debate, either everybody holds you can get your
object back as long as the second guy doesn't own it, and
the other approach here is, no, they actually debate whether you can
get your object back before you introduce תקנת השוק. takkanat hashuk. They
debate whether you have a right to get your object back, and
that's based even before יאוש, yei'ush, and that's based on whether we
agree or disagree with רב חסדא. Rav Chisda. Okay, now the גמרא
Gemara says like this. רב זביד אמר, Rav Zvid amar, gonna be
a lot of interpretations of this debate. רב זביד Rav Zvid says
כגון שנתייאשו הבעלים ביד לוקח ולא נתייאשו ביד גנב. kegon she'nityashu haba'alim
beyad loke'ach velo nityashu beyad gannav. Okay, what happened was that the
יאוש yei'ush happened after לוי Levi purchased it. ובהא פליגי, ubeha pligi,
this is the debate. מר סבר יאוש ואחר כך שינוי רשות, שינוי
רשות ואחר כך יאוש לא קני. mar savar yei'ush ve'achar kach shinuy
reshus, shinuy reshus ve'achar kach yei'ush lo kani. One holds you have
to go in the right order. First there's יאוש, yei'ush, then there's
שינוי רשות. shinuy reshus. That's what we've, this is an issue that's
been come up a lot. Right, and once there's יאוש, yei'ush, then
somebody else can come and take it and possess it. But if
it's the reverse order, he doesn't own it. So since here לוי
Levi first got it, there was first שינוי רשות shinuy reshus and
then יאוש, yei'ush, so לוי Levi doesn't own it. ומר סבר לא
שנא. umar savar lo shana. The other one holds it doesn't matter
and לוי Levi does own it. And since לוי Levi owns it,
therefore you have to go back. So, similar to a debate of
before יאוש yei'ush or after יאוש, yei'ush, actually that was saying there
was no debate, here we're saying there is a debate and the
debate is since the יאוש yei'ush came after שינוי רשות, shinuy reshus,
if you hold that that's קונה, koneh, then you have to go
to the גנב, gannav, and if you hold it's not קונה, koneh,
you can get your object back from the לוקח. loke'ach. רב פפא
אמר, Rav Pappa amar, now רב פפא Rav Pappa says בגלימא דכולי
עלמא לא פליגי דהדר למרי. biglima dechulei alma lo pligi dehadar lemarei.
When it comes to the actual garment, everybody agrees the garment goes
back to the original owner. Now, that might be because everybody agrees
with רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, or maybe he's even saying irrespective of
רב חסדא. Rav Chisda. רב חסדא Rav Chisda was talking about you
were מזיק, mazik, can you sue the second guy? But if you
have the actual object around, everybody agrees it goes back to the
owner. Okay, so what's this issue about ראשון rishon and שני? sheni?
והכא בעשו בו תקנת השוק קמיפלגי. vehacha ba'asu batakkanat hashuk kamifligi. The
question is whether there's a תקנת השוק takkanat hashuk in the case
where the גנב gannav is known. Alright, where you know about שמעון,
Shimon, do you have, well, let's see how the גמרא Gemara reads
it. Okay, and the ראשון rishon and שני sheni are going to
change from what we assumed. We assumed ראשון rishon and שני sheni
was גנב gannav or לוקח. loke'ach. So let's see, the גמרא Gemara
will explain what this means. Did they make a תקנת השוק takkanat
hashuk when it's הוכר הגנב? hukar hagannav? רב משמיה דרב חייא אמר
הדין עם הראשון. Rav mishmeih d'Rav Chiyah amar hadin im harishon. רב
Rav in the name of רב חייא Rav Chiyah says that the
דין din of the purchaser, okay, is with the first guy, meaning
the original owner. דינא דלוקח, dina deloke'ach, the purchaser דלישקול זוזי מגנב,
delishkol zuzei migannav, excuse me, not the first guy, not the owner,
the גנב. gannav. דינא דלוקח, dina deloke'ach, the rule of the judgment,
the case, the court case, the suing of the לוקח loke'ach דלישקול
זוזי מגנב delishkol zuzei migannav ולא עשו בתקנת השוק. velo asu batakkanat
hashuk. So he has to go and try to get his money
back from the גנב gannav and they did not make a תקנת
השוק. takkanat hashuk. Since שמעון Shimon is around, right, because the real
הלכה halacha is that ראובן Reuven should not be paying לוי. Levi.
It's his object, why should he pay לוי? Levi? That was a
תקנת השוק, takkanat hashuk, okay, in order to protect לוי. Levi. But
now we could say, you know what, that's only if לוי Levi
doesn't have anywhere else to get his money from. But if שמעון
Shimon is known and found and it's known that he's the גנב,
gannav, then we didn't make a תקנת השוק. takkanat hashuk. Let לוי
Levi get his money back from שמעון. Shimon. All right, you know,
that could still put a constraint on like free trade, but it's
assumed that he'll get his money back from. So דינא דלוקח, Dina
d'lokei'ach, where were we, דינא דלוקח דלישקול זוזי מגנב ולא עשו בה
תקנת השוק, Dina d'lokei'ach d'lishkol zuzei me'ganav velo asu bah takanas hashuk,
and they did not make a תקנת השוק Takanas Hashuk when when
you know who the גנב Ganav is, you don't get paid from
the owner, you get paid from the גנב. Ganav. ורב ירמיה משמיה
דרבי יוחנן אמר הדין עם השני. V'rabbi Yirmiya mishmei d'Rabbi Yochanan amar
hadin im hasheini. You deal with the you the second one. דינא
דלוקח דלישקול מבעל הבית. Dina d'lokei'ach d'lishkol miba'al habayis. I guess he's
called the second here because from לוי'ס Levi's perspective, the first person
he had dealings with was שמעון, Shimon, the גנב. Ganav. So therefore
the first opinion is he has to deal with the first guy
he had dealings with, the גנב, Ganav, and try to get his
money back from them once the גנב Ganav is known. And the
other one says no, he actually has a right to go to
the second person who gets into the conversation, the original owner, and
get his money back from him and they made a תקנת השוק
Takanas Hashuk even in this case, even if he can go running
after שמעון, Shimon, it's not really very fair to to poor לוי
Levi who just went to the marketplace and bought something, and therefore
he is entitled even in this case to get his money back
from ראובן. Reuven. Okay, ועשו בה תקנת השוק. V'asu bah takanas hashuk.
They made a תקנת השוק. Takanas Hashuk. Now the גמרא Gemara says
וסבר רב לא עשו בה תקנת השוק? V'savar Rav lo asu bah
takanas hashuk? Now are you going to tell me רב Rav holds
that they did not make a תקנת השוק Takanas Hashuk because according
to this read he's saying he has to go to the גנב
Ganav when you know who the גנב Ganav is? והא רב הונא
תלמידיה דרב הוה. V'ha Rav Huna talmidei d'Rav havah. רב הונא Rav
Huna was a student of רב Rav and חנן בישא Chanan Bisha
גנב גלימא ganav glima. and זבנה zavnah and sold it. Exactly our
case and ואתא לקמיה דרב הונא V'ata l'kamei d'Rav Huna and we
knew exactly who the גנב ganav was, we even named him. And
this case came to רב הונא Rav Huna and ואמר ליה לההוא
גברא V'amar lei l'hahu gavra and he said to that person, to
the original owner, שרי אפיטתיך. sharei apitateich. Go ahead and free your
collateral, meaning an אפיטתי apitatei is like an object given in collateral
for a loan. It was a way of saying you can get
your object back, but you have to pay the purchaser. So that's
a תקנת השוק. Takanas Hashuk. Here the גנב Ganav was known, and
this is a student of רב, Rav, and he's saying that the
owner still has to pay the purchaser, so you see they did
make a תקנת השוק. Takanas Hashuk. So the גמרא Gemara says no,
שאני חנן בישא כיון דלית ליה לאשתלומי מיניה כלא הוא דמי. Shani
Chanan Bisha keivan d'leis lei l'ishtalumei minei k'lo hu dami. חנן בישא
Chanan Bisha is different, he was of a like mafioso and therefore
even though you knew who he was, there was no way were
you going to be able to bring him to court and get
reimbursed. And therefore since you cannot realistically get your money back from
שמעון, Shimon, you do have a right to even in that case,
even somebody who would say that we don't make a תקנת השוק
Takanas Hashuk when שמעון Shimon is around, that's only when you realistically...
when the גנב Ganav is around, that's only when you realistically can
get reimbursed from the גנב. Ganav But if you can't realistically get
reimbursed from the גנב, Ganav. then yes they did make a תקנת
השוק Takanas Hashuk and you get reimbursed from ראובן. Reuven. Okay. כלא
הוא דמי. K'lo hu dami. אמר רבא. Amar Rava. Said רבא, Rava,
אם גנב מפורסם הוא לא עשו בו תקנת השוק. Im ganav mefursem
hu lo asu bo takanas hashuk. Now we're sort of moving beyond
the whole question of הוקר הגנב hukar haganav and all the five
different ways of interpreting that previous debate. And now he is saying
that if it was a well-known גנב, Ganav, like okay it's very
nice we want to protect purchasers and make it people able to
buy in a marketplace and not worry about their objects getting claimed
to be stolen, but that's only if you were not buying it
off of the back of a truck, right? If you actually were
buying it from somebody who you should have suspected was a גנב,
Ganav, then we do not want to encourage that activity, we actually
want to actively discourage that activity, and therefore we will not make
any תקנת השוק Takanas Hashuk in that case. Okay, now if the
guy is a known גנב, Ganav, meaning not that you know this
object is stolen, all right that maybe it's obvious, but even if
it's a known גנב, Ganav, you should not be buying from him
and we did not make a תקנת השוק. Takanas Hashuk. לא עשו
בו תקנת השוק. Lo asu bo takanas hashuk. והא חנן בישא דמפורסם
הוה ועשו בו תקנת השוק? V'ha Chanan Bisha d'mefursem havah v'asu bo
takanas hashuk? One minute, this case of חנן בישא Chanan Bisha we
just said he was this mafioso that you would never be able
to sue in court and they did a תקנת השוק? Takanas Hashuk?
Because because the whole case was what he said, pay the money
and get your object. So the גמרא Gemara says no, ניהי דמפורסם
לבישותיה לגניבותיה לא מפורסם. Nihei d'mefursem l'bishusei lignivusei lo mefursem. It's known
that he's a bad guy, maybe he's a violent person, but nobody
ever wasn't known that he's actually a גנב. Ganav, So there was
no particular reason to suspect that he was a גנב, Ganav. which
again raises interesting questions of when do we say you should have
known. All right. איתמר. Itmar. It was taught, גנב ופרע בחובו גנב
ופרע בהיקיפו לא עשו בו תקנת השוק. Ganav u'fara bechovo ganav u'fara
be'heikeifo lo asu bo takanas hashuk. Okay let's say ראובן, Reuven, we'll
have the same players, שמעון Shimon stole it from ראובן Reuven and
then he used it to pay off a debt that he owed
לוי. Levi. לוי Levi didn't purchase it in the marketplace, he already
owed לוי Levi a hundred dollars and he used the stolen object
to pay it to לוי Levi or he had a tab, that's
what היקיפו heikeifo is, and he used it to pay לוי. Levi.
In that case when ראובן Reuven comes along, he gets his object
back from לוי Levi and לוי Levi does not get to get
a hundred dollars from ראובן. Reuven. They did not make a תקנת
השוק Takanas Hashuk in that case. Why? דאמרי לאו אדעתא דהנך יהבית
ליה מידי. D'amri lav ada'ata d'hanach yahavit lei midei. Okay because you
did not actually shell out any money in order to get the
object. You had... shelled out the money before, and then this object
was given to you in payment. So ראובן Reuven is going to
take back his money, and then it's going to take back his
object, and then it's going to be the way it always was,
which is that שמעון Shimon is still going to owe you a
hundred dollars, right? We don't have to protect you; you didn't shell
out money for the sake of this object. משכנתא, mashkanta, now let's
say what happens is that שמעון Shimon gives it to לוי Levi
as collateral for a loan, and לוי Levi lends him a hundred
dollars and he gives it as collateral. So שוי מאתן במאה, shavi
masan be'me'ah, so if the object was worth 200 and לוי Levi
lent שמעון Shimon a hundred dollars, that's normally what you do, right?
Your collateral is worth more than the loan because you're going to
have to now take possession of it and sell it and whatever,
so that's the standard thing to do. So that's evidence that you
clearly lent him the money because of this object. So in that
type of a case, where are we, שוי מאתן במאה עשו בה
תקנת השוק. shavi masan be'me'ah asu bah takanas hashuk. There then לוי
Levi can go ahead and get his money back from ראובן Reuven
because they wanted to protect him because he laid out money for
an object that turned out to be stolen. שוי בשוה, shaveh be'shaveh,
however, if the collateral was 100 and the loan was 100, so
אמימר אמר לא עשו בה תקנת השוק. Amemar amar lo asu bah
takanas hashuk. They didn't make a תקנת השוק takanas hashuk because it's
more that you really trusted שמעון Shimon because you wouldn't totally lend
him the money based on the collateral, then you would have demanded
a collateral worth more. מר זוטרא אמר עשו בה תקנת השוק, Mar
Zutra amar asu bah takanas hashuk, they did do a תקנת השוק.
takanas hashuk. And in the parenthesis there's a version that says they
did do a תקנת השוק, takanas hashuk, that's actually what we're going
to say in the end anyway. Okay, so but that's that debate
because in the end you did lend money because of the collateral.
זבנה שוי בשוה, zabnah shaveh be'shaveh, now let's say you purchased it
for its going price, which is normally what the case would be,
so that's עשו בה תקנת השוק. asu bah takanas hashuk. That's so
if לוי Levi purchases from שמעון, Shimon, that's obvious, that's the standard
case. שוי מאה במאתן, shavi me'ah be'masan, let's say however לוי Levi
gave $200 to שמעון Shimon for this $100 object. So רב ששת
אמר לא עשו בה תקנת השוק, Rav Sheshet amar lo asu bah
takanas hashuk, they didn't make a תקנת השוק. takanas hashuk. Okay, the
way רש״י Rashi explains it, now you could have said maybe you
can't collect your full 200 from ראובן, Reuven, you could only collect
the 100, but רש״י Rashi says they didn't do any תקנת השוק
takanas hashuk because since you're so grossly overpaying, clearly you just wanted
to give שמעון Shimon the money as a gift and you're just
finding an excuse like when you buy a candy bar on the
subway from a person who's homeless and you give him $5, okay?
You clearly just wanted to give him the money. So there's no
תקנת השוק. takanas hashuk. So that's what he says. רבא אמר עשו
בה תקנת השוק, Rava amar asu bah takanas hashuk, they did make
a תקנת השוק, takanas hashuk, and רש״י Rashi actually says that that
means you can even get back your full $200. Obviously if ראובן
Reuven doesn't want to pay $200 for the object, he doesn't have
to. והלכתא בכולהו עשו בה תקנת השוק, ve'hilchesa be'chulhu asu bah takanas
hashuk, and the הלכה halacha is in all these cases that we
have debated, we did make a תקנת השוק, takanas hashuk, we're going
to incline towards protecting the purchaser. לבר מגנב ופרע בחובו גנב ופרע
באקיפי. lebar mi'ganav u'fara be'chovo ganav u'fara be'akipei. The one case not
was the case where it wasn't debated, where the גמרא Gemara said
it's obvious that if you first lent the money and then afterwards
the guy paid up with this object, so the money you shelled
out unrelated to the object, so then ראובן Reuven takes his object
back and now you're back to having שמעון Shimon owing you a
hundred dollars. All right, so that is a whole range of cases
about תקנת השוק. takanas hashuk. Now we're going to have a couple
more cases, actual real cases, not just theoretical. אבימי בר נאזי, Avimi
bar Nazi, this person by the name
of אבימי Avimi the
son of נאזי, Nazi, חמוה דרבינא, chamuh de'Ravina, the father-in-law of רבינא,
Ravina, הוה מסיק בההוא גברא ארבע זוזי. hava masik be'hu gavra arba
zuzei. So he had lent to a certain man four זוז. zuz.
Okay, let's call it $400. גנב Ganav, גלימא. glima Now this man
stole a cloak, אתיי ניהליה, atyei nihalei, and so he gave it
to this אבימי בר נאזי. Avimi bar Nazi. He gave him this
cloak to pay off his debt. אוזפי ארבע זוזי אחריני, osfei arba
zuzei achrinei, so then this one now that the debt was paid
off, אבימי Avimi bar נאזי Nazi lent him another four זוז, zuz,
אחריני. achrinei. לסוף אוקרא גנב, l'sof ukara ganav, and then the גנב
ganav was discovered, and now we're a question of תקנת השוק. takanas
hashuk. Is this a case of גנב ופרע בחובו? ganav u'fara be'chovo?
Because the original debt was paid off so that was a גנב
ופרע בחובו, ganav u'fara be'chovo, but then more money was lent, all
right? So maybe he's lending the money because he got the object
and then he shelled out money because of the object, so maybe
we would make a תקנת השוק. takanas hashuk. So let's take a
look. אתא לקמיה דרבינא, ata l'kamei de'Ravina, came to רבינא. Ravina. אמר,
amar, רבינא Ravina said, קמאי גנב ופרע בחובו. kama ganav u'fara be'chovo.
Pay off a pre-existing debt. So in that type of a case,
if it had just been that case, the owner would take it
back from this Avimi person and wouldn't have to pay Avimi anything
because Avimi didn't shell out the money because of this cloak. Okay,
and it wouldn't have to give him anything. But הני ארבע זוזי
אחריני, hanei arba zuzei achriney, but he says as for the next
four zuz that Avimi lent, שקול זוזך והדר גלימי. shkol zuzach v'hadar
glimei. So he says you have to, the רי"ף's Rif גרסא girsa
actually is לא הבו זוזי אחרי. lo havu zuzei acharei. For that
you have to pay the money if you want to take your
cloak. Now why? It's not exactly explained, but it seems like what
he's saying is it is because you actually gained my trust by
paying back your first loan that I'm willing to lend you now
money again. So the second loan actually was because of the cloak
that I got, and I never would have lent it had I
not got the cloak. So because I shelled out the money for
that, therefore they did a תקנת השוק. takkanas hashuk. That's what he
says. Where are we? מתקיף לה רב כהנא, maskif lah Rav Kahana,
Rav Kahana challenged this. ודילמא גלימא בהני זוזי קמאי יהביה ניהליה. v'dilma
glima b'hanei zuzei kamai yahviye nihalei. גנב ופרע בחובו גנב ופרע בהיקיפו.
ganav u'fara b'chovo ganav u'fara b'hekefo. So as you said, the first
four zuz was paid with this cloak, and that was a case
of paying a pre-existing debt, so you have no claim based on
that. And then והני ארבע זוזי בתראי, v'hanei arba zuzei basrai, and
the second four zuz, הימוני הימניה. heimoney heimaney. Maybe it was not
because the first debt was paid off. Maybe Levy just trusts Shimon
even and it had nothing to do with receiving the cloak. כי
היכי דהימניה מעיקרא. ki heichi d'heimanye mei'ikara. The same way he trusted
Shimon for the first four zuz, he trusts him for the second
four zuz. Why should we assume that the second loan was somehow
dependent on the fact that the cloak was given in payment for
the first loan? איגלגיל מילתא, igalgil milta, so the matter rolled around,
meaning the case was debated and discussed. מטא לקמיה דרבי אבהו, meta
l'kammei d'Rabbi Abbahu, came to Rabbi Abbahu. אמר, amar, and Rabbi Abbahu
said, הלכתא כרב כהנא, hilchasa k'Rav Kahana, we rule like Rav Kahana
that actually this is a case of גנב ופרע, ganav u'fara, this
is a case where we treat the second loan as independent of
the first, and therefore we only look at this case as a
case of גנב ופרע בחובו ובהיקיפו, ganav u'fara b'chovo u'v'hekefo, and therefore
he has to give the cloak back and cannot get any money
from the original owner. Okay, one more case. נרשאה גנב ספרא. Narsha'ah
ganav safra. Okay, this person from Narsha stole a sefer. זבניה לפפונאי
בתמנין זוזי, zabniya l'Papunai b'tamnein zuzei, he sold it to a person
from Papuna for eighty dollars. אזל פפונאי זבניה לבר מחוזא במאה ועשרין,
azal Papunai zabniya l'bar Mechuza b'mei'ah v'esrin, he sent it to somebody
from the city of Mechuza for a hundred and twenty. He made
a good profit. לסוף איגלאי גנבא, l'sof iglai ganva, then the ganav
was discovered. So this is a case actually where there's two לוקחs.
lokeach There's a Levy and a Yehuda. Alright, so now, and so
let's take a look. אמר אביי, amar Abaye, said Abaye, we won't
use Levy and Yehuda, we'll actually use the names here. ליזיל מרי
דספרא ויהיב ליה לבר מחוזא תמנין זוזי. leizil marei d'safra v'yahiv lei
l'bar Mechuza tamnein zuzei. Let the owner go and give the final
purchaser eighty. Alright, because that was the money that was paid when
it was taken from the גנב, ganav, it was eighty dollars that
was paid, even though this guy bought it for a hundred and
twenty. So let the owner get it and pay back the original
eighty. ושקיל ספרא, shakil safra, get back his book. ואזיל בר מחוזא
ושקיל ארבעין מפפונאי. v'azil bar Mechuza v'shakil arba'in miPapunai. And now let
the second purchaser, the guy from Mechuza, get back the forty dollars
he overpaid, or maybe it was a premium because he whatever, it
was a this guy bought wholesale sold retail, but maybe it was
an overpaid, but it doesn't matter. Okay, he's going to get back,
the owner pays the eighty which is what it was originally sold
for, and the second purchaser has to get his forty dollars the
difference back from the person who made the forty dollars profit. Alright,
because nobody deserves to, he doesn't deserve to profit off of stolen
goods. מתקיף לה רבא, maskif lah Rava, Rava challenges. השתא לוקח מגנב
עשו בו תקנת השוק לוקח מלוקח מיבעיא. hashta lokeach mi'ganav asu bo
takkanas hashuk lokeach mi'lokeach miba'ya. Rava said, listen, we're dealing here with
a question about making certain societal laws in order to encourage business.
So let's think about it from a policy perspective. If you want
to protect the first purchaser to get back the full amount of
money he paid, even if he overpaid, remember we said before, even
if he overpaid, he can get back his money from the owner,
then we should protect certainly the second purchaser who had no reason
to think that it was stolen. And therefore he should be entitled
to get back the money that he paid directly without having to
schlep after two people. Okay, so אלא אמר רבא, ela amar Rava,
so rather Rava said, ליזיל מרי דספרא ויהיב ליה לבר מחוזא מאה
ועשרין. leizil marei d'safra v'yahiv lei l'bar Mechuza mei'ah v'esrin. Let the
owner go and he has to give the person who has his
book a hundred and twenty, what that guy paid for it, make
that guy whole. ושקיל ספרא ve-shakul safra get your book back, וליזיל
מארי דספרא ולישקול ארבעים מפפונא, ve-leize marei de-safra ve-lishkol arba'im mi-Papuna, and
now you want to get reimbursed, so what are you going to
do? You're going to get 40 from this פפונא Papuna guy who
made the 40 profit and 80 from נרש Norsha who was your
original גנב. ganav. All right, and that is the way we פסקן.
pasken. All right, let's just get a little bit onto the next
page. This has been a very long דף daf and we'll get
a little bit on to turn this. We won't finish this דף
daf today. זה בא בחביתו של יין וזה בא בכדו של דבש.
Zeh ba be-chaviso shel yayin ve-zeh ba be-kado shel devash. Now one
guy was coming walking down the street carrying a barrel of wine
and the other guy a barrel of honey, and honey is much
more expensive per volume than wine. נסדקה חביתו של דבש ושפך זה
יינו והציל את הדבש. Nistikah chaviso shel devash ve-shafach zeh yeino ve-hitzil
es ha-devash. So the barrel, the guy with the honey barrel, the
barrel's cracking and his honey was spilling and going to waste. So
the guy with the wine spilled out his wine and saved the
other guy's honey because that gave him an empty barrel to save
the other guy's honey. Okay, והציל את הדבש לתוכו. ve-hitzil es ha-devash
letocho. So it says, אין לו אלא שכרו. ein lo ela secharo.
He only is entitled to getting his the fee for service. He
cannot get reimbursed for the lost wine. Nobody asked him to do
it. You know, thank you very much. How much does it cost
to hire somebody to save your wine? X amount. You know, why
should I pay you for the spilling, I didn't ask you to
do it? ואם אמר לו אציל את שלך ואתה נותן לי דמי
שלי? Ve-im amar lo, atzil es shelcha ve-ata nosein li demai sheli?
But if they stipulated and said, I will save yours if you
agree to pay for mine? Then חייב ליתן לו. chayiv litein lo.
Right, I will I'll save—excuse me, I read that wrong. I will
save yours if you will pay for me, I will save your
honey if you pay me for the cost of my wine and
he agreed, then you have to pay. All right, so obviously the
גמרא Gemara is going to say פשיטא peshita or whatever, but if
you stipulate then then you can get paid for the losses you
incurred. But if you don't stipulate, since I didn't ask you to
do it, you have no right to demand for me to pay
you for the wine. Similarly, שטף נחל חמורו וחמור חבירו, shataf nachal
chamoro ve-chamor chaveiro, if a like a wadi, like you know, like
a river came in a wadi and it swept away—you were walking
in the wadi and there was a flash flood or whatever and
it swept away your donkey and the donkey of your friend. שלו
יפה מנה ושל חבירו מאתיים, Shelo yafeh maneh ve-shel chaveiro masayim, yours
is worth a hundred, his is worth 200. והניח זה שלו והציל
את של חבירו, Ve-hiniach zeh shelo ve-hitzil es shel chaveiro, and you
could save one of them and you abandoned yours and you went
ahead and you saved your friend's donkey because it was worth more.
אין לו אלא שכרו. Ein lo ela secharo. So you can demand
how much it would normally cost to hire somebody to go and
jump into a river and save a donkey, but you cannot demand
the fact that you sacrificed your donkey to get it because again
the guy never asked you to do it. ואם אמר לו אני
אציל את שלך ואתה נותן לי את שלי, Ve-im amar lo, ani
atzil es shelcha ve-ata nosein li es sheli, but if the guy
said, if I go ahead and save yours will you pay me
back for mine? Then and he agreed to it, then the הלכה
halacha is חייב ליתן לו chayiv litein lo he has to give
it to him because that's what they stipulated. Okay, so the second
part that they stipulated is not such a חידוש, chiddush, but the
first part that you're not entitled is I think a little חידוש
chiddush because the guy in the end did you a טובה tovah
and you would think you would want to help him out there.
But nevertheless, since you didn't ask him for it, he has no
right to demand it. Okay, so let's take a look a little
bit at the גמרא. Gemara. ואמאי לימא לימי מהפקירא קא זכינא? Ve-amai
leima leimei me-hefkeira kachina? So the גמרא Gemara says why—why is the
guy who spilled the wine not entitled to being reimbursed from the
wine? Actually says the גמרא, Gemara, he's entitled to much more. He's
entitled to keep all the honey himself. This guy's honey was about
to spill out and go to waste. That made it at that
moment when nobody else was around to save it, that made it
ownerless. Something that was הולך לאיבוד holech le-ibbud is the phrase in
the גמרא, Gemara, going to waste. And therefore when the guy spilled
out his wine to get it, he should be considered having taken
possession of the honey from הפקר. hefker. It was ownerless at that
time. מי לא תניא Mi lo tanya do we not teach in
a ברייתא? beraisa? הרי שהייתה טעון כדי יין וכדי שמן וראו שהן
משתברות, Harei she-hayesa t'un kadei yayin ve-kadei shemen ve-ra'u she-hen mishtabros, if
somebody was carrying barrels of—you know, jugs of wine and jugs of
oil and saw that they were breaking and it was about to
spill, לא יאמר הרי זה תרומת מעשר על פירות שיש לי בתוך
ביתי. lo yomar harei zeh terumas ma'aser al peiros she-yesh li besoch
beisi. Don't say, oh my god, I'm about to lose this wine
and this oil. Oh wait, I have a way that it will
actually not hurt me. I have to take תרומת מעשר, terumas ma'aser,
one tenth from מעשר, ma'aser, if the person was a לוי Levi
it would go to a כהן. Kohen. I still have to take
תרומת מעשר terumas ma'aser from my wine or oil in my house.
So let me say this jug of wine that's about to break
and go to waste is תרומת מעשר terumas ma'aser on nine other
jugs of wine in my house. And this jug of oil on
nine other jugs of oil in my house and therefore נעבעך, nebbach,
you know, like it go ahead and it spilled, so כהן Kohen
doesn't get it, but I now don't have to give it from
my other stuff. I saved my money. It's like a joke, right?
Guy comes, people are sitting on a subway and guy comes and
sticks him up, says give me your money. So one turns to
the other and says oh you know what by the way here's
the $20 I owe you. Okay, so that's what it's saying. Why
can't you go, so you, so that's what you want to do.
You want to sort of not have to suffer the loss by
making it the כהן'ס Kohen's loss. It says you're not allowed to
do that. לא יאמר הרי זה תרומת מעשר על פירות שיש בתוך
ביתו. Lo yomar harei zeh terumas ma'aser al peiros she-yesh b'soch beiso.
ואם אמר לא אמר כלום, V'im amar lo amar klum, and more
than that, not only should you not do that, it doesn't take
effect. Why doesn't it take effect? Because at that moment, you don't
own them. It's considered ownerless. So the evidence here is not that
it's just not fair to the כהן, Kohen, but the evidence here
is is that it is ownerless and therefore it does not take
effect. So גמרא Gemara says כדאמר רבי ירמיה k'd'amar Rabbi Yirmiyah no,
it's like רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiyah says in another case similar that
we're going to deal with כשאקא ביצא בר כרכא לה k'she-aka bisa
bar karcha lah that when you have this type of a net
that you use in pressing wine wrapped around the barrel. So what
it means is the barrel was cracking and some of the wine
was going to get lost, but it wasn't all spilling out at
once. And therefore, since the wine was like dripping and it was
whatever, maybe you would have somehow managed to save it or, you
know, to save some of it. It wasn't like it was all
spilling. And in that case, we don't say it becomes הפקר. hefker.
Okay, so that's how that's so that's the case over there and
it's not הפקר. hefker. So since that's what he says about, I'm
sorry, so that's what he says in, excuse me, he doesn't say
in this case. In the case of the תרומת מעשר terumas ma'aser
it is all spilling and that's why it won't work. But רבי
ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiyah says in another similar case, if it's got some
net around the barrel and it's only dripping and not spilling and
it's not all about to spill out, it would not be הפקר,
hefker, and similarly in our משנה Mishnah by the honey, it's not
הפקר. hefker. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says why is the honey
not הפקר? hefker? And don't we see in this case when a
barrel is breaking and spilling out it all becomes הפקר? hefker? And
it says we're talking about a case where it's not all breaking,
it's not breaking and all spilling out at once and therefore it's
not הפקר hefker and therefore the guy has to give the honey
back and he can get only his fee. All right. So now
the גמרא Gemara says like this, ואם אמר לא אמר כלום. v'im
amar lo amar klum. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says כשאקא ביצא
בר כרכא לה. k'she-aka bisa bar karcha lah. Now ואם אמר לא
אמר כלום, v'im amar lo amar klum, is this really true says
the גמרא? Gemara? So now we've given this answer because from this
case about the תרומת מעשר terumas ma'aser we we're showing that when
something is breaking and spilling out, it's ownerless and it doesn't take
effect if you try to do תרומת מעשר terumas ma'aser on it
or anything else. Okay, so now the גמרא'ס Gemara's going to question
that statement. Is it really true that when something is spilling out
all at once, it's like it's ownerless and it wouldn't work for
תרומת מעשר terumas ma'aser or similar things? והתניא, V'hatanya, didn't we teach
in a ברייתא beraisa מי שבא בדרך ומעות בידו mi she-ba baderech
u'maos b'yado somebody is going on the way and he's got money
ואנס כנגדו v'anas k'negdo and a robber highwayman comes and sticks him
up, לא יאמר הרי פירות שיש בתוך ביתי מחוללין על מעות הללו.
lo yomar harei peiros she-yesh b'soch beisi m'chulalin al maos hallalu. He
shouldn't say the food I have in my house, let's say מעשר
שני, ma'aser sheni, should now be transferred to this money. You know,
and that way again, he saves the food in his home, you
know, maybe the money he would have had to bring up to
ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So okay, he loses something from it, but it's a
lot less of a loss and now it's the גנב'ס ganav's problem
to have this מעשר שני ma'aser sheni money. Don't say that. ואם
אמר דבריו קיימין, V'im amar divrei kayamin, it works. Okay, so says
the גמרא, Gemara, oh look, this looks like an exact case, something
is about to be completely lost and in the case before we
said that it, you know, that it it was ownerless and and
in this case, it seems like it works. Now you could have
made a difference. In the case before it was going to get
spilled and destroyed. In this case, somebody is stealing it. You know,
maybe you can now, you know, sue him and get it back
or something. But the גמרא Gemara is not going to make that
distinction. Why here does that work? Didn't we say there something is
about to be lost it becomes ownerless? Presumably again, the case of
an אנס anas is not just a normal גנב, ganav, right? Because
all the cases we've been dealing גניבה וגזילה gneiva v'gezeila we don't
say it's ownerless, but you know it's a case where it's like
a highway bandit and you're never going to get it back. Okay.
הכא במאי עסקינן בשיכול להציל. Hacha b'mai askinan b'sheyachol lehatzil. Oh, so
the גמרא Gemara says fine, similar to the answer about the the
net wrapped around it. Yes, there's a highwayman there, but you know,
you your you would be if you, you know, you could run
away and you could actually save yourself from having for, you know,
it might be that you can get out of it. And since
it might be that you can get out of it, therefore it's
enough you own it that actually will work. So the גמרא Gemara
says אי בשיכול להציל, i b'sheyachol lehatzil, if it's possible that you
can save yourself from from having to give the guy the money,
you could run away or something like that, לכתחילה l'chatchila מאי לא
יאמר? mai lo yomar? Why shouldn't you then go ahead and and
do it, transfer it? It's still your, you know, your money and
and whatever. And then if the גנב ganav gets it, then it's
his מעשר שני ma'aser sheni money. But you're not hurting מעשר שני
ma'aser sheni because it's totally your money. So גמרא Gemara says בשיכול
להציל על ידי הדחק. b'sheyachol lehatzil al yedei had'chak. No, it's only
through a lot of effort would you be able to steal it,
to to save it. So therefore we are so therefore, you know,
we don't assume you're going to save it because maybe you're not
going to go through that effort, especially once you've made it into
מעשר שני ma'aser sheni you're not going to go into that effort.
Now you have even less of a motivation to do it. All
right, but because it is maybe possible to save it, maybe save
it from giving or maybe להציל lehatzil here means after he takes
it, you could actually maybe find the גנב ganav or the גזלן
gazlan and get it back. So in a case like that, where
it actually would be, you know, possible... possible, it's similar to the
case of the netting around the barrel, and therefore it's not ownerless,
you might be able to get it back, it's not going to
all get definitely destroyed, and therefore it will work if you do
it, but you shouldn't do it. All right. So now the גמרא
Gemara says like this. The next line actually תוספות Tosafot takes out,
and I'm going to take it out just because the next גמרא
Gemara is much easier to read without it. The line is וכל
היכא דאיכא הפסד לכתחילה לא יאמר. V'chol Heicha De'ika Hefsed Lechatchila Lo
Yomar. This line is questioning this idea that when, you know, there's
going to be a loss, is that really true? Like it might
not totally get lost, but לכתחילה lechatchila you shouldn't do it. And
is that really true, this difference of like לכתחילה lechatchila and בדיעבד?
bediavad? That you shouldn't do it לכתחילה lechatchila if there might be
a loss. But let's not read it with that line. It makes
the whole next גמרא Gemara that that's what's being questioned. The easier
read of the גמרא Gemara is that it's saying: is this really
true that if something is about to get lost, that it doesn't
take effect? What did we say now? We've said in our משנה,
Mishnah, well, we started with this case about breaking barrels. Don't take
תרומת מעשר, trumas maiser, and it won't work. And that was evidence
that if stuff is about to spill and get lost, then it's
ownerless. So how do you explain our משנה? Mishnah? Okay, there's some
netting around it, it's not all spilling at once. How do you
explain the case about the money and the bandit? Also, you might
be able to go ahead and to get the money back from
the bandit, and therefore in that case, it's still owned by you.
But when it's completely going to a loss, then it's ownerless. So
the גמרא Gemara is going to question if that's really true. Okay,
let's take a look. והתניא, Vehatanya, but didn't we learn in a
ברייתא? braisa? הרי שהיו לו עשר חביות Harei Shehayu Lo Eser Chaviyot
של טבל טמא shel tevel tamei וראה אחת מהן שנשברה או שנתגלתה
vera'ah achat mehen shenishbera o shenitgaltah and you saw one of them
that broke or it was exposed, and when things get exposed and
liquids get exposed or whatever, they're אסור assur to eat afterwards because
of a concern of snakes. That's a whole discussion we won't get
into, well, a little bit. Anyway, אומר הרי היא תרומת מעשר על
תשע חברותיה Omer Harei Hi Trumas Maiser Al Tesha Chavroteiha and you
sort of said like before, you said: okay, this is about to,
this is breaking, it's all about to be destroyed, I'm going to
take this תרומת מעשר trumas maiser on nine other equivalent ones, just
like the case before. Where were we? הרי היא תרומת מעשר על
תשע חברותיה. Harei Hi Trumas Maiser Al Tesha Chavroteiha. You can actually
say it, says the משנה. Mishnah. You're allowed to say that. אחת
מהן שנשברה או שנתגלתה achat mehen shenishbera o shenitgaltah אומר Omer you
can say הרי היא תרומת מעשר על תשע חברותיה. Harei Hi Trumas
Maiser Al Tesha Chavroteiha. Now the reason is, is because it is
טמא. tamei. And because it is טמא, tamei, that's the key difference
why we allow you to do it לכתחילה. lechatchila. Since it's טמא,
tamei, you know, a כהן Kohen is not allowed to use תרומה
טמאה. trumah tmea. The only thing he might be able to use
the wine for is like, you know, you can get הנאה hana'ah
from it, you can't eat it, it's like an air freshener, but
the benefit is actually very, very small. So since the כהן Kohen
is not really losing out so much, well, go ahead and do
it. You really could have used it anyway, it's טמא. tamei. ובשמן
לא יעשה כן, Uveshemen Lo Ya'aseh Kein, but don't do that by
טמא tamei oil מפני הפסד כהן mipnei hefsed Kohen because what a
כהן Kohen can do with oil is he can use what he
would use oil for a lot, he can use it for lighting.
Okay, so even though he can't eat it, that the כהן Kohen
really would lose out on. What do you see from this? You
see that the only concern is whether the כהן Kohen is going
to lose out from the fact that this is going to waste.
But what is not a concern, and it's only a לכתחילה. lechatchila.
In the case of wine, you can do it לכתחילה, lechatchila, in
the case of oil, you can't do it לכתחילה, lechatchila, but it
is because of a concern for the כהן, Kohen, but everybody agrees
that it actually does take effect. Why does that take effect? Isn't
it all going to waste? How do you deal with that? Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says: אמר רבי ירמיה Amar Rabbi Yirmiya כשהקבה
של בית הבד כרוכה עליה. keshehakeivah shel beit habad keruchah aleha. This
is where ירמיה Yirmiya said his statement. Here we're talking about the
netting of the, you know, from the wine presses wrapped around it
and therefore it's not all going to waste. Okay, so we have
the case where it is spilling and going to waste, תרומת מעשר,
trumas maiser, the wine and the oil, and we say it's ownerless,
it doesn't take effect. So if that's true, why by our משנה
Mishnah does the guy still own his honey? Because it's dripping but
it's not cracking and all falling apart. In this case here, this
case of תרומת מעשר trumas maiser that's טמא, tamei, why does it
work בדיעבד bediavad and why is the only concern the loss of
the כהן? Kohen? But why does it work בדיעבד? bediavad? Similarly, it's
being wrapped in this netting and it is not all falling apart.
Okay, so we will I think we will end here and pick
up on this tomorrow.